It's such an interesting time to be
building software because things are
just changing like so fast.
>> This is Charlie Marsh, founder of
Astral, the Python DevTools startup that
was acquired by OpenAI. And I
interviewed him about how software
engineering is changing.
>> Now it's like when you put up a PR, I
actually have to review it really
closely because you're not like writing
it anymore. It's like the agent. The
cost of putting up a plausible PR has
gone to zero while the cost to like
review has remained the same. if they're
building so heavily with agents, like to
what degree do they need to understand
different parts of the code? I do think
it would be like really hard to be an
early career software engineer right
now. Here's the full episode.
What was the space like when you were
first getting into building these these
dev tools? Like why did you think it
could be better? Before I started
Astral, I was at a computational biology
company and I was like the second
engineer. I had no bio background and no
like ML background and so I was building
all the like software systems to like do
machine learning. Um, and so that was
like all Python. So I was like learning
Python. Then we had some Go and some
Rust. And so I just worked across lots
of different ecosystems. And you know I
think Python at the time like when I was
in that position I we were trying to do
a lot as a small team. So we had like a
very I mean not compared to large code
bases but we had a comparatively large
code base and it was really a small
group of us that were software engineers
trying to serve the rest of the team
whether they were like machine learning
researchers or scientists. So I had kind
of like worked across a bunch of
different ecosystems, seen a lot of the
tooling and now I was like working on
Python and we kept trying to get lots of
leverage out of the tools whether it was
like the type checker or the llinter or
the package manager like things were
scaling up. We were a small team. We
wanted to have like really good static
analysis, really good tooling. Um and we
kept running into like limitations
around it. I mean, I think there were
some I kind of like looked at the Python
ecosystem and I just didn't see the same
amount of like experimentation
that I saw in other ecosystems like in
the web ecosystem.
Um, there were a lot of things going on
that seemed pretty crazy. Um, and there
was a very intense focus on perform I
don't know about very intense, but there
was more of a focus on performance. Um,
and that started with like ESB build and
then which was in Go and then you had
like SWC and Rust and then you know bun
and and Dino and all these other tools
that came around and this idea that you
could have to native tooling for
JavaScript was like became very accepted
um especially as applications became
bigger and people were doing like more
and more stuff on their machine um and
that wasn't really happening in Python.
And so that to me was kind of like the
um the key question was like why can't
we have that? Um because I was seeing
all the stuff that was happening in web
um and I had I had done some rust I'd
done some Go. I'd like seen these
different tool chains and like how they
work what the experience is like the
user experience right mostly in those
cases. Um and then I saw Python and it
was like we had a smaller set of tools.
Um there were lots of interesting ideas
from other ecosystems that I didn't see
like represented. Um and uh they were
really all written in Python. And so
that to me was kind of like the
interesting question. Um, and it was the
first
uh it was sort of like the first thing I
uh I I asked when I started working on
this like when I released rough
um the title of the blog post was
something like Python tooling could be
like much much faster and and for me it
was really like this is a hypothesis
like could Python tooling be much faster
and then I built a prototype and then
that prototype was like yes I think it
could be. you wrote a post kind of like
exploring My Pi or publishing your
results using My Pi and the date on that
like nine days later you you published
the post that one that you mentioned
like it could be so much faster or
>> No, that's funny. I didn't even realize
that. Yeah. That those were so close
together.
>> Did you build that that proof of concept
in those nine days? Yeah, I wrote that I
wrote that blog post about basically
type checking at scale because I was
trying to think of what are things that
I learned that people haven't written
much about and then I started with a l
building a llinter because I thought it
would be much easier. I I think it
actually is a lot easier than building a
type checker. We're now building a type
checker and we have a type we have a
type checker. Um and so I can I can say
that I think building a type checker is
much harder. Um, but I started with a
llinter because I thought it would let
me like prove a lot of the same ideas
but in a smaller form factor like
building a startup or or just building
like a tool. You want to try to like get
something into people's hands that they
can actually use and that actually
proves out value like as quickly as
possible and also that lets you iterate
very quickly. And a llinter weirdly
ended up being like kind of the perfect
form factor for it because it it has
like a pretty simple core, but it's you
know then you have like tons and tons of
rules, right? And so it's like
extensible in a lot of different ways,
but people can get value very quickly
from a small core plus like some number
of rules. And so we were able to like
get something out there and then like
iterate and like ship like more rules
and more functionality and people could
like use it alongside other tools. Like
it was useful immediately which I think
is extremely helpful as opposed to
something like um I mean actually the
type checker would be a good example
like a type checker that's like 75% done
like isn't very useful. Um, same with
the package manager. Like these things
have to be I mean there are ways like I
think I would challenge those as like
blanket statements. But the point is
it's harder to ship something uh
iteratively that's like still useful to
users. Um, and I think that's like uh
one of the key properties and actually
like building momentum uh as like a tool
or something else.
>> When you posted that writing, what was
the reception? I mean the the blog post
itself like I published it and then it
was on Hacker News and it got tweeted
about a lot and it just created some um
you know some amount of uh excitement
and interest around it and those things
um I mean especially being on the front
page of hacker news I have a lot of
thoughts about I mean it's certainly not
uh it's like some percent luck um and
then some percent skill and uh it is
like a helpful thing but not a requisite
to success. Um, and it also doesn't like
guarantee success just because you got
something on the front page of Hacker
News. Um, like it's great. It's great if
you can, but um, there's a lot of
randomness to it. Um, I do think though
that
uh, well maybe a couple things. So one
after that happened like some people
started pay actually paying attention to
the project and so um I really tried to
like capitalize on that um by basically
by being like very engaged and so when
people would file issues I would like
aggressively try to like acknowledge the
issue as quickly as possible fix it and
ship a release like if you can do that
like within one day it's like a very
very powerful loop like you gain
supporters and like create more momentum
around the
Um, and there were also a couple like
high-profile people in the ecosystem
that started paying attention to the
project like Sebastian Ramirez who did
fast uh does fast API and you know a
bunch of other things. Um, and he's been
a great supporter of our projects too.
But like early on he was like oh this is
interesting. I'd like to use it and I
was like I basically asked myself well
what would it take for him to use it?
And then I just like tried to do all
those things. Um, so I tried to
capitalize on that. Um I think the other
is though um I do think a lot about like
developer marketing and um
it's sort of like a dirty word or like a
dirty expression like I I think like I
think a lot of engineers like want
technical products and tools to just
like win on their merits. Like the best
technical solution should just be the
one that like wins and grows. But um I
actually I I mean I have this sort of
like stupid hypothesis that there's all
these like there's like thousands of
like really amazing projects on GitHub
that like basically don't know how to
market themselves and so never like
never get discovered and never go
anywhere. Um, and I don't actually know
if that's true, but it's like sort of
how I feel about a lot of technical work
where it's like it's actually worth
looking at a project like Rough.
And um, when I think about like what to
put in the blog post or this extends to
like what to put in the read me or like
what to put in the you don't need like a
million emojis and like and like a
million screenshots of like everything.
What you need is like, okay, someone's
going to like like land on this page and
I have like 10 seconds to get them
interested in what I'm doing and help
them understand like why it might matter
to them and like why it's useful. And so
like that was like that's like the key
idea that I try to bring basically to
everything. I mean it's a little bit
depressing because it's like okay I only
have like 10 but like people people
really don't have like like this is like
the attention economy, right? It's like
um it's same thing with a blog post like
um ironically I used to look at a lot of
the OpenAI blog posts when I was at
Spring and we were trying to we were
doing like machine learning in bio and
we were trying to publish material to
like explain what we do but but we had
all these interesting insights like we
looked at the OpenAI blog posts
especially like the Dolly ones like the
older ones and we were all we were like
wow that's an amazing blog post because
if you read none of the text, you still
understand what they did and you're
still impressed by it. Like if someone
just goes on the page, they leave with
an impression and they have some
understanding. And I was like, "Wow,
that's like a really amazing thing." And
so when I write blog posts now, I'm
like, if someone just lands on this
page, I have to be prepared for the for
the large number of people who will only
read maybe the TLDDR, maybe look at the
first image, maybe read the headline.
Some people will read the full thing.
And so I should care painstakingly about
every word and everything it says, but
most people will read like almost none
of it. And so again, sorry it's a little
bit like it's a little bit depressing,
but like I do think it's worth thinking
about your audience and like how do you
how do you explain to them like why they
should care about what you're doing in a
way that's honest and genuine like not
like not like deceptive. Um but you do
have to think hard about um how do you
communicate like why something matters
to people very quickly. Could you give
an example of like what you did in your
case?
>> I think like for rough specifically, we
had a really good graph uh of the
benchmarks
>> um that we put in the blog post and that
like went it was like on Twitter and
like that that was like a priceless
graph basically. Um sorry, not in terms
of like monetary value. I just mean in
terms of like attention, right? It was
like oh that's like that's like really
obvious like what's happening there. I
think graphs of benchmarks can be uh
like a really powerful thing. Um all
benchmarks are bad and wrong in some way
and so there's a lot like there's a lot
more to like say about that like but um
but I do think like having a visual hook
that explains to people why they should
care and like what something is. um and
having a really strong tagline like I
would have to look back at what we had
but we were like okay we're going to be
like compatible with your existing stuff
and much faster and uh that's kind of it
and it's like okay well if it's
compatible and it's much faster like
that was like I was like why should you
care like it can be orders of magnitude
faster and it'll give you the same
experience you try to convey that like
as quickly as possible
>> right and even the I mean that blog post
header I mean, Python tooling should
could be much faster. Should be much
>> foc
provocative, I guess. Yeah.
>> I mean, I'm pretty against like uh
clickbait or like trying to be
misleading in like anything that we do.
Like we we you basically want to want to
balance like
creating like effective like effectively
communicating like the most interesting
pieces to people. Um, but you have to do
it in a way that like you believe is
like true and authentic. Um, like you
could lie about a bunch of stuff and
like post interesting things that are
like clearly provocative, but like I
don't know. To me that's just like why
why would I ever do that? That's like
such a losing battle.
>> What What do you think about I mean so
you have that graph and
>> I'm I don't know if the I see this a lot
though where the axis is not zeroed.
>> Oh yeah.
>> So it's you know it's it's all within
the range of like 50 to
>> chart crimes. Yeah. Chart crime. Yeah. I
wouldn't do that. Yeah. Yeah. I do think
like benchmarks are pretty um
complicated and controversial though.
And um maybe most people don't even see
this controversy, but like I do because
it's like it's just very like
performance is very nuanced. Um and
uh you know like like an you know you
have to think about like okay uh with
caching or without caching um those are
like pretty different or like uh
depending on the project that you're
running on uh the performance
characteristics will be like totally
different and like we see this like in
UV this is really hard because like
sometimes um you know UV is really fast
but sometimes your package install is
actually bottlenecked on um like a C++
build that's like totally out of band
and it's like okay well so how do you
like accur it's like I mean it's sort of
impossible to like accurately capture
like all of the different scenarios um
and so but it's also like a disservice
to users like not to try to communicate
to them
like the importance or like a real
representation of like what will the
difference in performance look like and
why does it matter and so you have to
balance those things. Um, which I think
is actually quite hard. Um, and a lot of
people tend to get it wrong. Um, and
maybe we've gotten it wrong a few times,
too. I'm like I'm happy to accept that.
Um, but I do think it's it's more
complicated than people think. Um, but
it's also I think a huge disservice not
to include like some way to try to
convey to people quickly like what
things feel like.
>> I think one of the things I'm most
interested in is like you you mentioned
that graph. I see that graph and like
you know the engineer in me is like how
how did you make it so much faster and
one of the things in the tagline is
Python dev tooling written in rust and
so I guess one of the first thing I'm
curious about is why did you choose rust
and what are the pros and cons of that
>> I would say I largely chose chose rust
for that project because of hype um like
I don't think at the time I was that
informed about a lot of the technical
trade-offs between those different
ecosystems. Um, and I hadn't really done
a lot of systems programming. And so
that's that's like the honest answer is
like I was seeing it in a lot of places
and it was growing a lot and people said
it was like it appeared to be sort of
like an accessible way to write my
impression was that it was an accessible
way to write uh high performance
software. Um, and and so I started for
that reason. Um,
in hindsight,
uh, I think it was, uh, an amazing
decision and I wouldn't absolutely not
do it differently and I think it was
like the best choice for what we're
building. Um, and and now I have a lot
more experience uh, writing Rust. it.
But it is funny because like I I do sort
of think that um if I had tried to write
this in like C or C++, I think I
probably would have given up because I
find those even now I find those
ecosystems
much more like intimidating, hard to
hard to access, hard to learn. I I have
often felt that like one of the great or
like underrated advantages of Rust is
basically like the tooling. Um cuz like
you drop in and you use cargo and that's
how you do like everything. And uh if
you clone, this isn't always true, but
like you know there are exceptions as
projects get sufficiently advanced, but
like if there's like a crate out there
um that we use and maybe I want to
submit a PR to it, I'm like extremely
confident that I can clone it and figure
out how to run and build it without
having to do like any work. like being
able to just clone and run like cargo
run or cargo build or cargo test. That's
actually like really amazing. Um
especially for someone like me who was
like new to systems programming and I
didn't want to have to figure out like
my whole like C++ like tool chain and
like build system like all this stuff. C
Rust was like opinionated about all
these things and so there were a lot of
things that were hard to learn. Um, but
uh but I was allowed to like basically I
was allowed to spend my time focusing on
the things that that like actually
should be hard to learn as opposed to
like all the other uh basically all the
that like you don't want to
spend time on like how do I get this
thing to actually like build and run and
blah blah blah. I think it has been an
extremely good bet for us. um like it's
scaled very well with the project and I
I mean we at OpenAI too are like we use
a lot of Rust and they're like betting
heavily on Rust and then you know me as
someone who builds software for uh
builds developer tools like tries to
build software for people to build
software I'm like very bullish on Rust
um uh like it's grown um enormously and
I think it will actually just like keep
growing enormously um at the same time
like I said this at the start I've never
been someone who's like super dogmatic
about ecosystems. Like I I think that
like all of those ecosystems have like
lots of redeeming qualities. Like I
think what's happening in Zigg is like
very interesting and like I wish I had
more time to like go deep on it and like
develop more nuanced opinions about like
what it does better. Like I'm sure it
does a bunch of things better than Rust.
Um and there I'm sure there are things
for Rust to learn from that ecosystem.
Um similarly people have a ton of
success building stuff in Go. I think
that's great too. I think like I think
all this stuff is great. Um, but I have
loved like using Rust and um, I have
complaints about it, but I view those
complaints as like things that we should
improve. Um, especially as like the way
we build software changes with with with
LMS.
>> So if sounds like you're saying C and
C++
today, you would not consider them
because their tooling is insufficient.
But Zigg, Rust, and Go are all, you
know, some spectrum of tradeoffs or
different things that
>> Yeah. I mean, I think I think a lot of
people would disagree with me, but like
I don't really understand like why
unless there are like very specific
technical
reasons um
uh or you're working with existing
software like basically I don't really
know why I would start a net new project
in C or C++. Um I I certainly would not
like at a personal level. Um I guess if
they're like the ecosystems you know
really well like that's then it makes a
lot of sense to do it. Um but if I was
like a new a programmer like looking to
learn systems or um if I knew those
languages equally well like I guess I
just don't understand like why I would
do that which I'm sure I'll get like
roasted for but I uh but I I just don't
really care. Like I now I actually care
about a lot of things that Rust gives me
that I didn't care about as much before
like memory safety. I don't think I even
understood or cared about what memory
safety was when I started working on
Rough to be honest with you. And now I
like I think it's like a pretty amazing
thing. Um is like you know memory I want
to build things that are like safe uh
that don't crash on users that are
really fast, really performant, um that
don't have to make compromises
basically. And like I feel like I can do
that in Rust. And so for me it's like I
don't know it's kind of like the perfect
language. I mean it's not the perfect
language but it is my favorite language
to use right now.
>> In today's world it's not unreasonable
that you could almost completely
transpile or convert your existing
codebase into any language of your
choice.
>> Like I saw I think it was the on bun I
forgot I think it was zigg to rust.
>> Yes.
>> Like all in one go. So like if you
studied some other language and you
thought it was better, you could totally
rewrite everything from Rust into I
don't know Zigg or Go, would you ever
consider doing that for uh the dev tools
that you've built for instance?
>> Yeah, it's such an interesting time to
be building software because things are
changing. This is not a novel comment,
but things are just changing like so
fast. like I I didn't I didn't really
program with agents at all until like
Christmas, like December break basically
of this year. Um and or of last year
rather and like that's really not that
long ago. Like I mean I was like using
cursor and stuff but like I wasn't like
now like I I haven't edited code in an
editor in a very long time. Like I
everything I do goes through codecs and
like even if it's like small edits I'm
just prompting and kind of like it's
like it's it's completely different. Um,
and that's not that long of a time,
right? And so, uh, I don't know what's
going to look like in six months. hard
to say. But so that you know the reason
that I mentioned that is
like I think bun
uh like doing that rewrite it's like I
wouldn't do that right now but I'm
actually like I'm glad that they are
like pushing that they are experimenting
and pushing the envelope of like what's
possible and and they're doing it in the
face of like a lot of criticism and um
it will be interesting to how it plays
out for users because I think a few
different things I thought about is like
oh reasons not to do that like one is
okay uh maybe you don't understand the
code anymore right like if the code got
completely rewritten quote unquote then
as a human like you may not understand
any of the code anymore um and that can
be a big problem um I I think there are
mitigating factors around that which are
like they tried to do a very direct
transpolation quote unquote I mean it's
not exactly a translation but they tried
to do like very onetoone on. Um, and so
that hopefully helps with like
understanding all the abstractions. If
they're building so heavily with agents,
like does it even matter like to what
degree do they need to understand
different parts of the code? I actually
don't know the answer to that, which is
where my everything's changing so
quickly comes from. It's like it's
actually a little bit hard for me to say
right now how much that actually matters
anymore of um if they did transpile the
whole codebase like how well do they
need to understand things at different
levels of abstraction like they should
you know it's it's actually a very like
I think a complicated question um so one
reason is like how well you understand
the code that's confusing thing the
other is like you're kind of trading
like when you do a rewrite like that
you're trading
known ISS issues for like new unknown
issues. Like imagine you merge that and
it closes like 50 open issues on GitHub
in a literal sense. Okay, that's great.
But you may have now caused like 50 new
issues that didn't exist before that you
don't know about. Um because your test
suite is even a great test suite is only
like an approximation of like your
program's correctness. Um there's like
Hyram's law which is like anything
uh I'll get the phrasing wrong, but I
mean the gist is basically any like
implementation detail in your software
of someone eventually becomes to rely on
that. Um and so even things that aren't
encoded as behavior become part of your
API whether you like it or not. Um which
is a scary thought, but basically that
means that even if you pass your whole
test suite, there's probably like lots
of behavior that was like implicitly
encoded in your program that's like
changed. Um, and the unfortunate thing
is you end up pushing that onto users.
Like they are the ones that have to run
into that and then report it and figure
out what went wrong. And so that's like
that's actually like my main area of
concern with an automated rewrite. I
actually trust the models enough that I
would consider allowing them to do it,
but the scarier thing for me is
basically what's the impact for users?
Like how do you and how do you roll that
out safely? So um I don't know. It's
kind of a we we're not going to like we
don't have anything planned to like do
that for any of our own projects, but it
is like an interesting question. I mean
I I think maybe like the third piece
that I do think about especially right
now where like everything's changing so
quickly and
there's you know the basically the
spectrum of like how you write software
um has like uh gotten like way wider.
This is a terrible analogy, but there's
like so many different ways to build
software now. Like there's like the true
like Andre Carpathy definition of vibe
coding where you're like don't look at
the code at all. Um all the way to like
you know don't use LLMs and and blah
blah. There's like a lot of different
stuff in between. Um and I actually
think that like right now I have pretty
different approaches to different
projects in terms of what I do. like we
like I built, you know, a tool uh last
week that was it's basically personal
software. It's like a custom Rustliner
to help us enforce certain things in our
projects that I've like always wanted to
enforce but didn't fit into existing
tools. And I didn't read any of the
code. Um like GPT55 did the whole thing.
And um and it's like okay I can have a
really different standard for that than
UV because that project we are the only
users. It's uh it's easy to tell if it's
correct or not you know not to go too
deep into the weeds on like what the
project does but like we know if the
output is like incorrect um and uh and
there's no other users. UV is relied on
by millions of you know millions of
engineers and like all the like every
single company and so it's like we want
to be really careful about like what we
ship there and how. Um but there's a lot
of room right now I think for exploring
like how we build software. Um you do
have to be careful like what is your
what what project are you working on and
like what responsibility do you have to
users and that's not meant to be a a
subweet on like what Bun did. It's just
like how I think about how do we want to
push the envelope in like different
places,
>> right? I mean, to me that just reminds
me of the prelim trade-off, the like
navigating the I guess the risk of the
code change and how much you verify it
cuz
if it's not risky, like it's a internal
dev tool that only you and I are using.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Maybe I just I ship it with I
just, hey, stamp it. It's don't worry
about it. It's not going to break
anything. But if it's, you know, the the
critical thing that's blocking customers
from checking out or something, maybe we
maybe we have two people reviewing it
and there's like a lot of checks in that
part of the codebase. So I it feels like
the similar spectrum is just now like
there's a new level of trying less which
is not just like a human doesn't even
interact with it. just, you know, ship
it and maybe you just stamp it and no
one ever even looked at it,
>> right?
>> Um whereas before at least to have
written it a human would have had to do
it.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I mean I think
>> well okay a lot of reactions to that.
So, one I I guess like the other thing I
would just say quickly about is like um
sometimes I go over to their repo and
it's like it's just so different than
our repo and it's very interesting to
look at because if you look like
basically the number one contributor is
like the the Robo bot and sometimes
you'll click on PRs by humans and
there's like human accounts talking back
and forth but it's clear that all the
comments were written by agents and
you're like wow this is like very and so
I look at that but my perspective on
that is basically like Okay, I'm glad
that people are like that they are like
experimenting with like different ways
to like build software. Like I don't
know that I'm ready to do that but like
but like I but I do think that like a
lot of basically a lot of things are
going to change and I think it's very
interesting to be experimenting. So I'm
glad that they are experimenting with
things is my sorry is my like conclusion
there.
>> Do you block like if people are just
submitting a full agent stuff on your
repos is that
>> we do. Yeah. So we have an AI policy
now. um which isn't intended to be like
anti-AI but it's really like intended to
um because I mean we develop like very
heavily with LLMs um like that is true
um but it's it's more intended to be
like how do we um
how do we
like retain like useful contributions
while filtering out like net negative
interactions from the repo Because like
a contributor coming in and
uh you know posting a comment that their
agent wrote and then we like ask them a
question and then they just paste like
the agent response back like there's
like very little value in that, right?
Like we could just like ask the question
to to the agent, right? And so the
things like we want to retain the things
that are useful from like human
contributors which is like you know like
insight like ways to reproduce like the
information we would need to like plug
it into our agent because there's no
point in just like having a conversation
with an LLM on a GitHub issue right like
it doesn't really do anything for us. Um
and uh so we we you know our policy is
roughly um you should you should like
you need to like understand like what
you're pasting in u or or what you are
submitting right which I sounds like a
low bar um but it's not and uh
>> how do you police that
>> if we can't tell and it is agent written
then I guess that's fine right
um but you know at least right Now,
there are just lots of tells and like um
uh you know, being way more thorough
than a human would ever be, including
way too much detail, way more
formatting,
um using terminology that a human
wouldn't use, like inventing random
jargon, um tons of links, like I guess
the broad sign would be like putting in
way more effort in ways that aren't
necessary in a way that a human wouldn't
is like almost always agent authored.
But it's been Yeah, it's been
challenging. I mean, I think the hard
thing Zigg has a much more strict LLM
policy, which is like no LLM written
code or no LLM assisted code at all in
the project, which is very different
than us. I mean, like all of my PRs now
are are LLM written, right? LLM written.
Um uh and they had a blog post about
this idea of like they saw called it
something along the lines of like
contributor poker where it's like you're
kind of trying to place like bets on
contributors like like historically in
open source when a contributor came
around um they might be like new to the
project but they could show like signs
of promise or like they're really
engaged or really interested and like
you give them feedback they take the
feedback and they fix up their PR and
then the next time they put up PR
they've learned from that feedback right
it's the same way as like mentoring a
new engineer who joins your team. It's
like they learn from feedback, it
compounds, they get better, and then
they can actually mentor someone else in
the future, right? And so you're making
investments in people in a way. It's the
same for open source. It's like you want
to um I thought about this a lot
historically. It's like you want to like
invest in good contributors who are
going to grow to help others and be
maintainers in their own right. that's
kind of gone um if for PRs especially
that are written by agents because
people don't really learn anything like
someone can put up a PR that's written
by an agent and you leave comments and
then they take your comments and put
them into the agent and then update the
PR and then merge it and it's like that
there's no compounding feedback. Um and
so I actually do like understand that
perspective a lot um of uh like the the
contract between like maintainers and
contributors is like pretty different
now. Um and you know relatedly again not
a novel insight but the cost of putting
up a plausible PR has gone to zero. Um
while the cost to like review and vet
applausible PR has remained the same and
um is very high like especially for the
projects that we work on where
um
you know I'm not trying to like
overstate it. They're just like hard
projects. Like TY is our type checker.
Probably hard hardest project I've
worked on technically to like get a
change merged because of the like
complexity in the architecture but also
like the problem space like it's just
very very hard. Um and so if someone
puts up a plausible PR to to TY it might
take them two minutes and then it could
take us you know an hour to understand
it. And so it's created like very poor
dynamics
in open source. And um I I don't know
how we've solved that. Um I think it
will like continue to get worse um until
hopefully it gets better in some way
like we find ways to solve this. Um but
it's certainly something we've
experienced in our projects,
>> right? It sounds like review is becoming
more and more of a bottleneck. Is for
that bun rewrite. Do you know if it was
human like humans read that code or that
was just kind of
>> No, I don't think it was human reviewed.
Yeah. So, it's just YOLO rewrite the
whole thing. And
>> yeah, I mean, in a way, I think it's
like I think they did have and I'm
excited for like at least at time of at
time of recording, quote unquote, you
know, Jared hasn't published the blog
post yet, which is like I mean, he keeps
making jokes about how like the blog
post taking way longer than the rewrite.
Um, but I'm actually really interested
in the blog post because I think they
did have a pretty
like sophisticated approach to like how
the rewrite worked. Um, which will be
interesting to read about. like it
wasn't just like they had one prompt
that was like rewrite this in in Rust.
It was like they tried to have um at
least my impression from looking at the
PR is like there were um there were
actually like different phases of the
rewrite and like each file had to go
through like a couple different phases
that had like ways to validate whether
it was correct or not. So um uh the
answer is no though. I like I don't
think a human was reading like
significant amounts of that code. Like
it's just not possible basically.
What if we we both agreed today that
Zigg was objectively better than Rust
and then someone on your team said, you
know, I can do this rewrite into Zigg.
Would Would you block it if
>> I think I would block it? I I think
um I I don't know whether I'd be right
to do so, but I think like we as a team
like aren't there yet. Um and uh and
maybe we will like get there and that's
how we will feel eventually. But like
right now I I think we just feel like
right now um there's still a lot of
value in like deeply understanding like
our code and our tool chain and like the
ecosystem. And so I would say we don't
want to do that. Um but
might depend on the project. I don't
know.
all the things that you've built,
they're like an order of magnitude
faster than what was available at the
time.
>> How much of a difference did Rust make
on that graph?
>> I think it so it depends a bit on the
project. Um I think I think in rough
a lot of it was just Rust. Um and then
over time I think we've
um
improved on that a lot because
uh because you can even look at the
history of the project like the project
I mean hopefully no one like hopefully
this is still true but like basically
over time the project gets faster um and
sometimes that regresses but like uh you
know you basically maybe I put it
differently you could write rough you
know in like a couple different ways all
in rust and they could have really
different performance characteristics.
So that's just to say that like I I
generally think of rust as like the the
floor or the uh the sort of like the
baseline performance that you get is
going to be significantly better. But
you still have to you still get a lot
more out of like thinking deeply about
performance and design. Like if you take
the same program in Rust and in Python
like exact same implementation to to the
closest approximation you can get like
the Rust one will be faster but you can
then take that program and you can
probably optimize it another like 10x um
I don't know about 10x but my point is
even within being written in Rust
there's like a ton of room for how to
make things more performant how to write
really performant software and like
again when I started working on Rough um
part of my my goal was to learn Rust and
so I wrote I did write a lot of like bad
code Um, which is fine. Like I shipped
something out that was really helpful to
people. Um, but it's gotten a lot better
I think over time and like we've made it
more and more performant. Um I think in
UV
there was more um sort of like
architectural innovation beyond just
being in Rust especially because UV like
so as a package manager um you're doing
a ton of IO like downloading f and you
know downloading files over the network
unzipping things like writing them to
disk moving them around the llinter
doesn't have to do as much of that I
mean it has to read all your files but
there's there's not like a sign a huge
amount of IO
the package manager is like mostly IO.
It's like and then you're trying to do
things like very efficiently. So um
there it was more I mean rust was
important but I I do think that in UV
there's more um you know architectural
things that we did or like ways that we
thought a lot about performance like the
c the design of the cache is like very
very intentional um and makes it so that
um
like repeated installs of the same
package on your machine are like are
like near instant because of the way
that we like lay out the cache and the
way that we install from the cache into
your projects. Um, it basically means
that if you've installed a package
before, installing it again is extremely
cheap. Um, and both in terms of disc
space and time. Um, and so that was like
that's like a very different design than
um, any of the other like Python package
managers had. Uh, so again, it kind of
depends on the project. Um, I do tend to
think that like whether you're writing
code in Rust or in Python, there's like
always room to like be thinking about
performance. like you can always make
things faster or slower. Like even if
you're writing in Python, like you can
still make things like much much faster
um by like thinking harder about
performance and design. Um so it's some
mix but it depends on the project.
>> Open AAI, Enthropic, Cursor, and
Verscell all use this product to make
their lives better. And the problem it
solves is when you're building SAS or an
AI product and you want to sell to other
companies, there's all these
requirements you need to meet. There's
SSO, there's skim, there's arbback,
there's audit logs. These are all things
that take time to integrate, but aren't
the main focus of your app. Work OS is
an API layer that lets you meet all of
these requirements in just a few lines
of code. So, let's say you have a new
SAS product and you want to sell to
other companies. work OS will solve all
of these critical feature gaps for you.
You can check them out at workos.com to
learn more and get started and I
appreciate them for supporting my work
and sponsoring this podcast over the
course of the project. Do you have a you
know top few things that were
implementing the project that were
technically challenging or most
interesting to you? I really like this
optimization that Andrew on our team um
who goes by burnt sushi. He's uh he's
the author of Rip Grap and bunch of
other things. He's like really amazing
engineer. He did this really cool
optimization around how we represent
versions. It's pretty cool. I mean
basically like if you think about
resolving and installing like a very
complex Python project um we we it turns
out that we have to like parse and
create lots of versions like as in 1.0.1
1.0.2 to like we just like version
objects within the program like we end
up parsing and creating a lot of those
and it turns out that actually like
allocating that memory um was expensive
um given like the scale like the number
of times we were doing it and he came up
with a representation where we can
represent um like 90 something% of
versions with a single U64 integer. So
it's just like way more efficient. Um
and uh the benchmarks around that and
the implementation were were very cool.
It's like one of the coolest PRs I've
read, I think. Um, in TY, which our type
checker, there's a lot of like very
interesting performance work that's
happening, especially to make it um
incremental. So like uh uh TY is
designed to be um a type checker and a
language server. And
the whole system is like highly
incremental. So the idea there is like
if you're in an a text editor and you
open up like one file, you don't
necessarily want to like have to type
check your entire project like all your
dependencies, every file in the project
just to get analysis for that file. Um
like because you don't need to. Um so so
how do you make that work? That's like
that's sort of like uh I would that
would be like lazy. You want to be lazy.
Um, but the other piece to that is like
if you have a file open and you edit it,
um, or you have like two files open, you
edit one of them. Um, you only want to
recmp compute like exactly what you need
to recomputee. Like you don't want to
have to go and retype check like the
entire codebase again. Um, especially
because maybe you're working in a big
project like PyTorch and it's like you
have two files open, you edit one of
them, you don't want it to like and then
you save, you don't want it to take like
two seconds to like retype check the
project and like give you a new
analysis. So the whole system is built
around queries um which is pretty
interesting. This is more of like a
macro design thing. Um but uh we built
it on top of a framework called Salsa
which is um also what Rust Analyzer uses
which is like the popular Rust language
server. Um and now we've
intentionally or inadvertently become
like like very large contributors to
Salsa. Um but but the whole the whole
system is built around that which has
been like very interesting
architecturally.
>> Interesting. So it's it's lazy so it
doesn't type check the whole codebase
and it's incremental. So
>> yeah the incremental part is the thing
that's hard because you kind of need a
way to basically like uh it needs to be
able to model kind of like a dependency
graph of like everything that's
happening in the code. Um and so then
when you change something we want to
just like flow the data back through all
the different pieces like only the
pieces. Yeah. Um so that took a lot of
work. um but uh is it has come together
um and I've been doing a lot of
optimization lately with codecs um
because
it tends to be very good um at
especially at like micro optimizations
like if I'm like and in TY in particular
we also need to think a lot about memory
um not just speed because if you work on
a very large project like you don't want
it to take like many many many gigabytes
of you know just to like run your
language server like ideally you want it
to be like relatively efficient. Um, so
like I spend a lot of time now kind of
like continuously optimizing like memory
usage and performance and I can just set
a goal that's like try to reduce memory
like salsa memory by like 1% on this
project and like you can't do like these
these things that you might like like
try to do. Um,
and it's very good at just like coming
up with um like very reasonable things.
And so I I don't know. I find that very
cool because it's kind of like you can
almost have like continuously op I won't
say self optimizing that's like a built
grandiose but you can kind of be like
continuously like just like optimizing
your software. Um so uh I've been
enjoying that a lot. Um but uh but most
of those are like um yeah trying to find
ways to like represent things uh that
take up less memory um or uh trying to
come up with like sometimes it's like
trying to come up with broader redesigns
to like fix pathological performance.
>> That one optimization where with the
version numbering and seeing that
you can limit it just to like use 64. If
you think back to some of these more
creative optimizations that were done
that was in the human era, do you think
if you just I don't know ran codeex and
you're like hey just don't break things
but lower do you have faith that it
would come up with that or is that kind
of a a step above what
>> that's a very interesting question. If
you just at least in my experience like
if you just ask these things to reduce
memory or improve performance by some
you know moderate percentage it will
typically come up with things around the
edges um as opposed to like larger
uh redesigns or reconsiderations but you
can get to those larger redesigns if you
prompt and collaborate with the agent.
And so if you sort of ask like well like
should we be thinking a bit bigger about
like why we have to represent the data
this way like you can you can get to
like bigger ideas. And so that might be
an idea that you could have gotten to
with prompting if you were like um you
know okay let's start by like profiling
and figuring out where we're spending a
lot of time and then maybe the you know
would eventually come back to you and
say like we're spending a lot of time in
like version parsing and like version
like ball like version drop and version
allocation like blah blah and we' be
like okay well like how could we
represent these like more compactly and
it would probably start by finding like
micro optimizations in the
representation of like well this field
like you combine these two fields like
if you buy it's like blah blah blah but
I think if you kept pushing it like it's
plausible it would get there um but
that's not the thing it's going to come
up with by default. Mitchell Hashimoto
um who was like one of the Hashiore
founders works on Ghosty um he had a
post that was insightful I thought last
week or this weekend about a renderer he
wrote where it was like a really
terrible renderer. I'll probably butcher
the the tweet, but it was like it was a
really terrible renderer and then he
hadn't like intentionally and then he
had an LM like optimize it and it made
it like 10 times faster and he's like
great, right? Actually, no. like my
handwritten version was like a hundred
times faster and it's like you know like
you lose if you're not like using your
brain to like think about from first
principles like how fast should it be
and like how should the system work like
then you just like ship all this these
like accumulated like I mean I I won't
necessarily call it slop but it's like
you just ship these like things and
you're like yeah oh my god I made it 10
times faster but really it should be
like 100 times faster and so I think I
don't know it shouldn't be controversial
there's still a lot of room for like
using your brain Right. And like uh uh
but I do I do think it's like I struggle
with this stuff a lot. I mean like I'm
changing how I write software a lot and
um you know I've had people on my team
like because I'm using agents a lot and
and also was you know to some degree
trying to like
push our team to like use agents more. I
mean I mean some of that for me came
from a place of like we build tools for
software engineers and a lot of our
users are now using agents and so if we
like if I if everything good that we do
that's an exaggeration but if everything
good that we do comes from like
understanding our users very well and
like how they work then like we should
probably be like using agents that we
understand like what it's like to build
software for with them so that we can
build better tools for our users. That
was part of my motivation. Um, and part
of it was just kind of seeing how it can
change like how you work. And I don't
know, I think I'm shipping a lot more.
Um, but but it has been like um it has
been like a a difficult process. Like
I've had people on the team tell me um
uh which I think is great that they tell
me this. Um but they're like, "Oh, it
used to be the case that like whenever
you put up a PR, I could like review it
pretty minimally because I had a lot of
confidence in it and like your work. And
now it's like when you put up a PR I
actually have to review it really
closely because you're not like writing
it anymore. It's like the agent and I
was like wow that's like that's like
very interesting to they're completely
right which is and like and the same
thing happens to me. It's like if I go
to sleep and then wake up in the morning
and look at one of the PRs I put up and
I'm like wait this is terrible. You know
what I mean? It's like you can it's it
it's just uh it is easy to trick
yourself into like
basically believing work that isn't at
the same standard as what you would do
before. And I don't think I think we
have we don't really know what to do
with that. Um, and I'm kind of learning
and getting better and like I mean this
was I think I'm doing a lot better job
now than I was in like probably you know
like February or something where I was
like I was just like you know fully
agent killed and I'm like now I'm like a
little bit more like um but so my point
is like that was like a par powerful
kind of like moment for me when someone
on the team said that and I was like wow
like you're right and I and I see that
in other people on the team's work too
like it's not just limited to me but
it's like um you know it really guys
throw a lot of things on their head.
>> If you generate pure slop, that's that's
easy. But I think there's this gray area
where you you generate partially AI slop
or it's, you know, it's it's acceptable,
but it's not at the bar that you used to
have. Do you What are the tactics that
you've used on the team that have worked
for combating this kind of gray area AI
slop?
I'd like to get to a world.
We're not here and I don't know if we'll
ever get there. I'd like to get to a
world where if you put up a PR and it's
all green, then the odds of it getting
merged are like extremely high, right?
Um because that would mean that like you
have automated verification for like
most of what matters. Um and we have a
lot of that in our projects and we've
tried to add more over time and I think
it's helpful. Like we have like in TY
especially we have um
uh tons of like benchmarks like that run
under val grind like um through through
co cod speed like on every PR. So we get
like and that includes memory. So we
benchmark like memory usage and um uh
simulation time and wall time like on
every PR. And then we also have a really
big suite of ecosystem
um tests. So basically every time you
put up a PR we run before and after on
like a bunch of projects in the
ecosystem and then we create this report
of the diff of all the diagnostics like
the errors that got removed and added
and everything. So we have like over
time we've tried to do like more and
more uh these are important honestly
even before we had agents like these
were like we basically couldn't build
without these things but the point is
like I want to have like more automated
verification um and try to get better at
that um and that includes things too
like um we basically assume now that
anyone on the team that puts up a PR has
already run that through codeex review
like probably several times. Um, and
that's basically an assumption. Um, I
mean, we could automate that process,
but
>> codeex review is just an agent reviewing
the code and double checking.
>> Yeah, it's just running codeex and then
just doing slash review.
>> I see.
>> That's it. Yeah, it's not that fancy. I
mean, it's not sorry, it's not that
sophisticated, but it's just like
because now it's like if if a
contributor puts up a PR, that's the
first thing that we do,
>> right?
>> Um because it tends to find good things.
Um, you know, I think I think the things
that I've uh so so like basically I
think one bucket is like how do you um
create more like automated systems that
just help get things make sure things
are right. Um, and that also includes
things like trying to improve your like
agents.mmd file over time. Like if there
are things if there's feedback you're
giving in a review that the agent's not
respecting, try to find a way to help
the agent learn that. even learn um uh
skills like we have some shared skills
on the team stuff like that like none of
this stuff is very sophisticated by the
way it's like pretty simple um the other
piece is like how do I make sure that I
put in the work to ensure that I'm
creating a good PR um and so for me
that's like
I really should understand it's again it
sounds like a really not it really
sounds like a low bar but I should
understand like each line in the PR.
I know it's crazy. Um uh but also I do I
do try to um review each PR myself in
the GitHub UI. This is something I've
always found really helpful. Like if you
actually just like open up your PR and
click files and read through it as if
you were a reviewer, you tend to find
things that you would miss if you were
just looking at your local diff. I find
that very useful. And then the other is
trying to like encode skill. I guess
this is a little bit more in the first
category, but trying to encode skills um
or trying to encode in skills uh things
I'm contin consistently getting wrong
that the agent is getting wrong. Like I
had like a recent example would be I I
found that I was often getting feedback
on PRs that was of the form
what you know this condition here this
like if statement what case is this
intended to catch because if I comment
it out all the tests pass and so I was
like okay I should probably have a pass
before I put up any PR where I have the
agent like go through and check like are
these conditions still relevant or are
they left over from a product refactor
or something else. So, um I I don't
know. I'm not I'm still learning, but
those are some of the things I've been
doing. Yeah, it's again I think it's
like a it's a pretty hard time to be
like building software, but I felt for a
long time or I had a fear that AI was
going to make us more productive, but
that programming would be like a lot
less fun. Um because I just like love I
just like love programming. Um uh and I
was like, "Oh, now I'm going to have to
spend all my time like reviewing code
and like prompting this like idiot agent
to like that's like keeps getting things
wrong and like but ultimately like is
probably more productive." Um I actually
feel way better about that right now
than I did like a few months ago. And I
don't I don't exactly know why. Like I
think
I think it's because
well I think the agents getting better
and the tooling getting better and me
getting more comfortable with it is one
factor. I think the other is um I've
grown to appreciate more of
the the the kinds of things that like
working with agents has unlocked like
the cost of running an experiment is
incredibly low. There's so many things
I've wanted to try or like questions
I've wanted to answer that I could now
answer like almost instantly. Like I
like a sort of a dumb example, we UV in
UV um everything is snapshot tested. So
like basically all of our testing is
effectively
running UV and verifying the output.
That's how we test like basically the
entire program. Um and so that mean we
have a lot of tests that means we have a
lot of test output and the test output
is um it actually ends up in the test
files. So we have rust files like we
have a file called like lock rs that
tests all our UV lock. It's all our UV
lock tests and it's very very long in
part because it has all the lock output
snapshotted in the test. And I was like
hm like what if we stored the snapshots
in separate files?
like would that somehow make our like
compiles faster because then you don't
have technically that's like rust code
and so it's like would that all
disappear and like would that make like
our builds faster or blah blah blah and
I'd always want to do that but it
sounded like like to do that to do that
experiment as a human would be like
extremely painful because you have to
convert all of those tests and I just
had an agent do it in the background
while I did a bunch of other things and
I got a bunch of data on it and the
answer is no but but it's like I you
know what I mean like I I I mean, sorry,
the answer is a little bit more nuanced.
It actually does have a good impact if
um if you're just iterating on the
snapshot outputs, you no longer have to
recompile your program at all because
this outputs are stored somewhere else.
Anyway, that's the thing that makes a
difference on. But my point is I'm just
like running experiments like that like
all day like like trying things that
were used to be hard like used to cost a
lot to um to answer. Uh the work of then
going from that to like production,
there's still like real work there. Um,
but so you know, I think one piece is
the tools and the agents getting better.
The other is things that I just wouldn't
have been able to do before that I can
now do like incredibly easily. And then
um and then the third is I think I'm
more and more realizing that like a lot
of the value I get from building
software is not uh is retained because
some of it is like thinking hard about
like the not it doesn't have to be
typing out the code but it's like
thinking hard about like the layout of a
data structure. A lot of it is merging a
PR that closes a user issue. I get a lot
of satisfaction from actually like like
fixing and improving something. It's not
necessarily just from typing out the
code. So, I I do feel for people a lot
who
feel like they're losing something by
like working with agents because I do
feel that myself. Um, but I feel better
now than I did a few months ago about
my like like what it's like to work as a
software engineer with agents.
You mentioned in the like one of the
performance optimization examples you
said if you just unleash codecs it kind
of does this local optimizations and
it's very
>> good at that but it's not
>> great at kind of like some of the I mean
today it's more human ingenuity of like
system level um
>> optimizations and it kind of reminded me
of this tweet that you had you said it
says I I'm slightly concerned by how
much garbage I would be turnurning out
if I was trying to use these tools
without significant software engineering
experience.
>> I remain concerned about that.
>> Yeah, it it it reminds me and similar to
what uh the Mitchell Hashimoto tweet
that you said. It was like there's a
very big difference between Codex go and
do this versus um you know, you are like
wielding it like this tool and you're
kind of like proddding in the right
direction.
>> Yeah. Um, but yeah, I was curious your
thoughts on that because it seemed like
it went pretty viral and I think a lot
of people are thinking about that.
>> Like being a great software engineer is
like uh
like more like useful than ever. like I
I don't like it's um you know it's still
the case that I I think that the people
on our team who are like the strongest
like software have the strongest
engineering skills are like the most
effective like even at using agents um
and uh you know it's funny because
there's a lot of talk about like token
maxing I don't know if you're familiar
with this right yeah the idea of like
should you have a leaderboard for
example this is getting tweeted about a
lot companies that have token
leaderboards and it's like how do
like creates terrible incentives to just
like use as much tokens as possible. And
it's funny because we do uh that does
get tracked or sorry there's not a
leaderboard but like token usage is
something you can like look up for
example you know internally I mean and
um it's interesting to look at because I
I don't care like who on the team is
using the most tokens like and there are
people on the team who are like I'm like
actively trying not to care about that
like being where I am on the token
leaderboard which I think is like great
like I I don't care like they don't have
like they should just do like do a great
job and like that's fine. I don't care
if they use a lot of tokens or not. But
it is interesting to look at the token
leaderboard because um some of the
people on the team who are most
productive are like using like a lot of
tokens, right? It's like like there is
like a correlation. I'm not saying it's
causal, but I'm saying like I do think
that a lot of great engineers like are
able to like use agents very effectively
and like to hopefully to like multiply
their skills. Um, so I uh I do think it
would be like
really hard to be an early career
software engineer right now. And um I'm
not spending that much time with early
career engineers right now just based on
like at Astral we're just a very small
team um and we tended to hire very
senior. Um but uh it's it is sort of
hard for me to think about like what
what would we uh like how would I learn
basically like what would the iteration
loop be um I would be like learning from
codecs I guess um as opposed to
uh like
um
the other way around basically I mean
like like a lot of the times I'm
actually like instructing codecs right?
And like trying to correct it and
providing a safeguard on it. Um or opus
or whatever you're using. Um and so uh
yeah, I think I just don't know like
where you would get it would just be way
too easy to fall prey to like a lot of
the bad things that happen when you use
agents. You built this proof of concept
in uh in Rust and it was really
wellreceived, but why did you start a
company around it and how did the like
the raising go and all of that? What was
the motivation there?
>> Yeah. Yeah. So, um I left Spring um I
was actually convinced to leave by a
friend who uh very close friend who um
left Meta around the same time and he
was like, "We should start a company
together." And I was like, "Okay, fine."
Um I mean, it wasn't quite, you know,
that simple. Uh but uh but I did, you
know, I left and and then we we kind of
went into the, you know, the quote
unquote idea maze of like what do we
want to build? like we we went into it
not knowing what we wanted to build and
we spent a bunch of time exploring the
ven diagram of ideas of like there were
things he was interested in that I
thought was were not interesting and and
vice versa and there was some stuff in
the middle and we spent time exploring
the stuff in the middle but then in all
my spare time I was working on like
developer tools and because that's what
I thought was really interesting and he
it wasn't quite like a fit for him
basically um but around then I was
working on rough I was working on a a
couple other projects that you can see
in my GitHub that are like I don't know
probably not as interesting but they
were like I was like experimenting with
like lots of different things at the
time like I was pretty interested in web
assembly. Um I wrote a sort of like a
CI/CD
toolkit in Typescript. It's sort of like
you wrote pipelines in Typescript and it
transpiled them to Docker. And I was
like, "Oh, this could be cool." Like,
well, I don't know. I was like building
a lot of stuff. And at that point in
time, I I decided I wanted to start
developing relationships with investors,
but that I wasn't ready to raise money
because I didn't know what I was
actually going to build. And so, my
thinking was I'm going to try to like
get connected to some people who like to
invest in this kind of stuff. Um, with
an eye towards reaching back out to them
in like like 3 to six months and being
like, "Hey, we had a great conversation.
Now I'm working on X." So, that was my
thinking. So I got connected to a couple
investors who invest in inf like
software infrastructure and developer
tools. Um and I had some good
conversations and then like the problem
is things just can move really quickly
and so I didn't actually expect to like
start raising so soon but I effectively
got convinced and and at the same time
rough was growing a lot and so I
effectively got convinced that there was
enough there to start a company which is
a very interesting process. I was like I
was like I don't know quite know how
this becomes a company but I was
effectively convinced that there was
enough there to build a company which is
interesting
>> by the investors.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Um which I'm grateful for.
>> The other thing I was convinced of um uh
was uh uh which is funny is um if I
hated it, I could stop in like six
months. It's like if you decide it's not
for you, you could like give the money
back. actually said that.
>> Yes. Which I actually think was
brilliant cuz like I was probably never
going to do that but it did make me feel
like there was less pressure.
Um so uh sorry very round very very like
weird roundabout details but um but
basically like uh I was like working on
rough more like full-time eventually and
then um uh it was kind of like uh I
would say collaborative with like the
potential early investors where it was
like we would just have like long
conversations about like my ideas and
then um it basically become clear that
it was like there's enough here like you
and I like wrote out kind of like a
product roadmap which honestly like a
lot of it stayed true to like what we
ended up building um what we've ended up
building so far at least and um and from
there it basically became like uh yeah
we want to fund you like here are the
terms that we would do and I was like oh
wow okay so I guess this is happening so
so uh it was it was just an interesting
and I had never done anything like this
before I mean I was just I was just you
know an IC software engineer my whole
career um and then I uh suddenly I was
like starting a company and Um,
it's funny cuz I actually think like the
decision to like go all in and like
start the company
wasn't that stressful. I actually think
a lot of the stress came later as the
company started to succeed. Um because
at the beginning I had I kind of had
nothing to lose. But then as the company
started to succeed um you know I was
like oh wow like the company's kind of
working like what's going to happen from
here and I had a team of 20 people who
were depending on me and so um I don't
know just for me as a founder it was
like um I'm pretty like riskaverse but I
actually found that starting the company
was
uh an easier it was it was an easier
decision than maybe some of the
stressful things that came later uh to
navigate. Um, but it happened very
quickly and sort of unintentionally and
in in a symbiotic way with investors
which was which I I I hadn't really
anticipated.
>> I didn't expect the the investors I mean
cuz I thought the founders hungry for
the fundraising and go please fund me
but the investors were like
>> I think it can happen a million
different ways and like
>> um
>> actually I mean we did three fundraises.
We did a C series A and a series B. Um,
we actually never even announced the
series A or the series B. They were I
mean they were announced in the
acquisition blog post, but we sort of
complicated. It's like we we basically
just never got around to it. Um, and uh
>> why don't you guys publish it? Because
isn't that good marketing for talent?
>> It's good marketing, but basically like
we there kept being like reasons that we
like wanted to wait a little bit and
it's also like to me it always felt like
a lot of work. And then I was like, it
just never I honestly just never felt
like the most important thing because we
were like building a lot of stuff and
like the company was going well and I
was like I don't we don't need the
marketing. Uh we did finally plan to
announce it but then we got bought so
didn't happen. But um but uh each of
those
each of those fundraises was um uh was
like preemptive basically like like
initiated by investors. Um which was uh
which is like uh I mean it's like
fortunate because like the company was
like going well and people wanted to
invest. Um but it was also just like a
funny position to for me to be in I
guess. Um, uh, I think I, uh, I think I
was just always a little bit
conservative and I wasn't super
aggressive about trying to go out and
raise money. Um, and, uh, but but we
were lucky enough to be building things
that people really, um, had a lot of
confidence in or had a lot of belief in.
>> That probably gave you a lot of
negotiating leverage because like one of
the best positions you'd be in is that
you you're willing to walk away. You
don't need it. And by definition, you
didn't even come there to begin with.
They came to you and said, "Please take
the money."
>> That's true. Yeah. Yeah. I wouldn't say
I'm a great negotiator, but um yeah, I
guess at least I had a strong hand. But
we were very lucky with investors. We
had we had amazing investors. Um like
super supportive and really like aligned
with how I wanted to build the company.
Um like never any
conflict, never any like pressure to do
anything specific. um like just support
and um maybe the only thing maybe the
only piece of consistent feedback is
that I could have been more aggressive
uh and but I I don't know it's like uh
just in terms of like scaling and
growing and doing more but I liked the
way that we operated and um yeah we just
had such good we had such good
experiences with our investors too so I
felt lucky about that because it can
easily go the other way. I imagine if
someone invests there's a promise of
future revenue but how how does this
company make money because you guys give
away your software for free right so
>> yeah we launched a commercial product in
like August of last year
>> um and it was sort of it was called py
it was kind of like a hosted
um counterpart to UV so like a lot of
our a lot of UV users will purchase like
a private registry software instead of
using in the public registries either
for like security or maybe they need to
publish their own private artifacts,
things like that. And we basically built
our own private registry that had some
first class support for you for UV. Um,
and it let us solve a bunch of problems
that we saw, you know, in our issue
tracker around users using other
solutions. Um, also let us build
something really fast because we like
vertically integrated the client and the
server. There were like special things
they could do to be like really fast and
really easy to use and and all that. And
we spent a while um selling that uh and
um our revenue actually grew like pretty
well. Um I mean it wasn't like I think
in this era of AI you're constantly
hearing about fastest company to go to
100 million in revenue and and things
like that. It wasn't it didn't look like
that. Um but we were definitely able to
sell this to like some big enterprises.
Um and I mean the cool thing was we had
very good because we built the open
source and everyone was using our open
source. We had a really good funnel like
like we had a small number of extremely
high quality coh customers is the way I
would put it. Um so the general idea for
like how we wanted to make money was
keep uh like build open source and like
the tooling the tooling remains like
free open- source like entirely
non-commercial and then we build
software that's kind of like the natural
next thing you need when you're using
our tooling. So if you're using UV you
there are probably sol problem there are
likely problems we can solve for you
with like a private registry. Um and
then the funnel is like people using UV
they have these problems and then we
sell them the registry and the registry
was meant to be like one piece of a
platform of like a bunch of different
things we sell like a Python cloud. Um,
so that's what we were like building
towards. Um, uh, I mean part of the cool
thing about the, um, acquisition is
we'll be able to take parts of that
platform and make it basically freely
available. Um like we did just as an
example a a big part of that was um
uh we did a lot of like in Python um you
know there's a big part of the community
that uses Python with GPUs like PyTorch
and and then there's like a whole
ecosystem around PyTorch of like
software that kind of like builds
against PyTorch. Um and we that's for a
variety of reasons the ergonomics around
that are are not great. um like it can
be kind of hard to work with, hard to
install, hard to get hard to install the
right version. Depends on the GPU that
you have and like what version of CUDA
you have installed and like all this
stuff. And so we we kind of tried to
solve that in a in a certain way. Um
where we built our own distribution, you
could think of it kind of like a Linux
in the sense of like a Linux
distribution like we pre-built a lot of
things like that that all worked
together and made that available to
customers. And so now we can actually
take that and just make that like freely
available to everyone because we're no
longer uh we no longer are trying to
build like an independent business.
We're just trying to build uh great
tools that like grow a broader
ecosystem. So I mean more more to come
on that, but that's been kind of like
one cool thing that I'm I'm excited
about. as a first-time founder,
especially with the engineering
background, was there anything that kind
of like a surprising learning or
something where you would share that
with someone if they were an engineer
and they were going down that founder
path?
>> There are so many different ways to do
it. Like I I'm actually like not a huge
fan of people giving startup advice in
general because so much of this industry
is like um survivorship bias of like you
could give the exact same advice to like
you know like basically you can go to
like two talks and people give you like
two like incredibly successful founders
give you like completely contradictory
advice and you're like I don't really
know what to do. Um and I I tend to view
that as like you've got to figure out
what's true to you. Um, and so, you
know, like there's all these decisions
you have to make like in person versus
remote, right? Like have a principle and
like stick to it. Like either one can be
great. Like we built the whole company
remotely. It went super well. Like it
was great. Um, do I think there are
benefits to being in person? Of course.
Um, would I have been able to hire the
team that we put together if we were in
person? Absolutely not. And so like, you
know, there are trade-offs to all these
things. You just have to like be
principled and figure out like what's
what resonates with you. um you know
like uh and there's there's like a
million of those decisions that you have
to think through. I feel fortunate in a
lot of the ways I got to run the
company. Like I I tried to spend like
very minimal time fundraising and with
investors and I tried to optimize for
investors I really trusted as opposed to
trying to talk to a billion different
investors and like pit them all against
each other to get the best terms. like
my my goal was always like find a
partner that I really trust and get good
terms and then move quickly to spend as
little time on fundraising as possible.
Um, and so, you know, think about think
about what you care about and focus on
that. There's no right answer to a lot
of this stuff. I got a lot of advice to
get a co-founder when I first started
the company and I basically ignored
that. I mean, I I like Well, sorry. I
did ignore it because I didn't get a
co-founder, I guess. But like I for me,
it was kind of like um
uh I kind of knew they were right
probably, but I didn't really have
someone in mind. I didn't want to force
it and so I just didn't. And um you
know, over time I felt like it would
have been helpful
to have someone to uh that's kind of
like in like in the trenches with you in
the same way. Um, but you know, you find
other ways to acco um to compensate for
it. Like I don't know, I lean on my wife
a lot, probably more than I, you know,
more than I should. Um, probably more
open with my employees than I otherwise
would be, which is, I think, which can
be good or bad, but it's like I share a
lot with of, you know, with with the
early team, like especially when I need
advice on things. Um, try to build a
network of like other founders. Um,
especially here in New York, I have like
a pretty good group of um, there's like
six or seven of us who we try to get
dinner twice a year. Doesn't sound like
a lot, but everyone's busy.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
>> Um and and that's been like a really um
Yeah, that's been like a really helpful
like support system. So, you just find
other ways to to compensate, but um
yeah, it's uh I don't know, there's no I
really don't I really think there's not
one right way to do it. Um
yeah, and it extends everywhere. I mean
like also I don't know everyone on X is
talking about like um you know like
should everyone in your company be
working seven days a week this kind of
thing and it's like
I don't know like we just built a very
different company and we were able to do
it like that was not I mean I work I
work basically all the time um and
that's a choice I made um and that I'm
like very happy with but I don't expect
people on the team to work all the time
and I want it to be a company where um
you know you can be highly highly
successful working normal hours um but
also where you're rewarded for you know
your output and your performance um and
I try to keep all those things in sync
but like again there's no one right one
way to do it there's no one right way to
do it like other companies that is their
culture and that's what they want to do
and like sure whatever like if that's
what you sign up for like just make sure
that you're honest about like what
you're doing so I don't know I just
think figure out what you care about and
in my opinion And don't focus too much
on how you think you should be doing
things. Think about how you want to be
doing things and what actually fits with
how you want to work.
>> What's your top book recommendation?
Whether technical or maybe something
that helped you as a founder.
>> I don't read a lot of like technical
material. I have definitely watched a
few talks that were very influential to
me, which is a little bit different.
>> What are those talks?
the Zigg creator uh Andrew Kelly um had
a really good talk about like data
oriented design that like I learned a
lot from. I mean even apart from
learning things, it sort of inspired me
to like look at software quite
differently. Um and so I think about
that talk a lot. Um interesting.
>> Yeah, things like that.
>> It's really good. Yeah, it's about um
well, I haven't watched it in a while,
so I'm probably mess it up, but it's
like uh a lot of it's about basically
design decisions they made in like the
Zig compiler and um and uh just like
thinking about like memory and
allocation and all this stuff. And I was
like, I watched that when I was pretty
early in my career of like systems
programming and I was like, "Wow, like
these people really care about what
they're doing." And I was like, "That's
cool."
Yeah.
>> Yeah. And then last question is, if you
could go back to the beginning of your
career, like right when you graduated
college, what advice would you give
yourself knowing what you know now?
>> I don't know. It's so hard to give
myself advice without feeling like I
have all this hindsight bias, you know?
I mean, I think
I guess I guess there are some things
where I'd basically like tell myself
that it is the right decision and I
shouldn't worry so much, but it's hard
to know how that would have played out,
you know, if I did it a thousand times
over. Um, but for example, like I think
when I left school and I went to work at
Khan Academy, part of me was definitely
like, wow, should I be taking more of
like a big tech job and am I going to
really regret not having that experience
or like um or like I mean the like like
the the Khan Academy like pay was good,
but it was like the big tech pay was was
certainly like better and I was seeing
my friends get like huge bonuses and
like all this stuff and I was like I
felt sort of insecure about should I be
doing that and I think it actually, you
know, in the long term really paid off.
Like I think I mean maybe it would have
been great but like the experience I had
was really what I wanted and I thought I
made that decision for the right reason.
So I think some of these things are like
I don't know everything happens for a
reason you know and it's like have some
faith in like what you're doing for the
right you know for the uh if you're
making decisions based on principles
like I think it can it can work out.
when we started this conversation, you
said, you know, the the reason you got
into what you got into is because you
tried all these different ecosystems and
you had a a broader perspective. I
imagine if you went to Google and you
just kind of I don't know used Google's
closed thing and then you might not have
had the same insight.
>> Yeah. And you know I I I I think about
this with Spring too because Spring like
I was there for four and a half years
and um and then I left right as they
decided to do like you know like a pivot
and then they ended up uh like joining
Janentech. But we had set out to build
like this kind of crazy drug discovery
company. We were focused on aging and it
was all with like computer vision. It
was like very very ambitious what we
were trying to do. Yeah. Yeah. And then
afterwards I was like ah like the
company didn't like it didn't have like
the huge exit or like the huge you know
we didn't achieve like all of our dreams
like did I waste all my time and
ultimately I was like no because I
learned by being an early employee even
and like seeing all these stages I
learned so much about how to run like my
own company and also all the technical
learnings that I rolled into my own
company. So again I feel bad I feel
weird giving this advice because it's
like everything work everything has
worked out really well. But I like I I
feel like there are moments in time
where I sort of doubted some of my
career decisions. And then in hindsight,
like you can only connect the dots
looking backwards. Like it like
everything kind of added up to finding
the thing I really love, which is like
building tools and um and feeding into
that.
>> Awesome. Well, thank you so much for
your time, Charlie. I really appreciate
it.
>> Yeah, thank you. No, it was super fun.
>> Hey, thank you for watching this
podcast. If you liked it and you want to
see the show grow, please support with a
comment or a like. Also, if you have any
recommendations for people you want me
to bring on, please drop a comment.
Guests like Barbara Liskoff, Mike
Stonereaker, Mark Brooker, these were
all people that I brought on because
someone left a comment. On another note,
aside from the podcast, I'm working on
building the ergonomic keyboard that I
wish existed. Here's a glance at the
prototype. It's a split keyboard, so
there's two sides. Um, this is in the
case, but yeah, we launched on
Kickstarter and we hit our goal within
eight hours of launching. I really
appreciate it if you were one of the
people who grabbed one of the early
units. Um, we're now working on the long
journey of building the tooling now and
so if you still want to pick one up,
I've left the late pledges open on
Kickstarter, so you can grab one there.
I'll put a link in the description.
Thank you again for watching the podcast
and I'll see you in the next